A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Audiovisual materials FA750
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Audiovisual materials
undated
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA750
1 Film Reels
Conditions Governing Access
When requesting to view films -- please refer to the Title and the AV Number (example: AV 1902).
If the item does not have a designated AV number, please refer to the Title and the Film Number (which consists of a combination of Roman numerals and alphanumerics - example: III 14.1-6).
Conditions Governing Access
All inquires to view films require advanced notice of at least 24 hours, and may necessitate notice of up to one week. Individual items, including those that are not available in modern formats, may be restricted from scholarly access at the discretion of RAC.
Ford Foundation; Ford Foundation
- Ford Foundation Films, 1
  Arrangement
  Alphabetical
  Scope and Contents
  The films included in the collection are the products of various grants and internal initiatives, dating from the early 1950s.
  Biographical / Historical
  The Ford Foundation is a nonprofit grant-making organization with an extensive history of international leadership in economic development, human rights and microfinance, as well as major U.S. causes, including the environment, civil rights, legal aid, and women's rights, and such domestic challenges as urban development and reproductive health.
  - 4 Women Artists, 1977 (Reel AV 1904)
    Conditions Governing Access note
    All inquires to view films require advanced notice of at least 24 hours, and may necessitate notice of up to one week. Individual items, including those not available in modern formats, may be restricted from scholarly access at the discretion of RAC.
    Scope and Contents note
    A documentary about traditional arts and storytelling in southern US communities, with interviews and footage of Eudora Welty, Pecolia Warner, and others. Directed by Bill Ferris. Funded by the Rockefeller Foundation, National Endowment for the Humanities, Mississippi Arts Commission, and the Ford Foundation. Copyright 1977, Center for Southern Folklore.
  - Abstraction (Reel AV 1957)
    Short film presented by the American Federation of Arts about the physics and characteristics of abstraction. Distorting physical items from science, nature, and intangible items in math and art can all be understood as abstraction. Abstract concepts in design, art, and language are shown. An ACI Release. Produced by Roemer-Young Associates. Ford Foundation grant from 1966 to American Federation of Arts.
  - Abstraction, Sound, color, 11 minutes. Only available on 16mm. (Reel AV 2004)
    Conditions Governing Access
  - All About Life (Reel AV 1780)
    Episode of TV series from unknown network hosted by Dr. Ron Pion. Features a pregnant woman and a panel of children who are queried about pregnancy and childbirth. Produced by Jeff Shiffman, a King Community Services Program.
  - Alternative Sentencing (Reel AV 1902)
    Overcrowded prisons and outdated systems in Georgia required the state to explore nontraditional sentencing structures - their successes are documented in this short film. At the threat of federal involvement, the state designed new alternatives to prison time. The film shows several tiers of options for nonviolent criminals, and discusses the challenges and accomplishments of the programs. Funded by the Ford Foundation and the JFK School of Government at Harvard. Produced by David Jordan, copyright 1988 by GDC.
  - Aptitude Testing (Reel AV 1847)
    Showcase of education and training opportunities for young people in Nigeria. A four-year study by the American Institute for Research and the US Agency for International Development produced an aptitude test, which was incorporated into school and professional systems throughout Nigeria. Details of the test and its outcomes are presented. This film is presented by the Ford Foundation in cooperation with the public authorities of Nigeria.
  - Are You Listening: Household Technicians (Reel AV 1900)
    An episode of the series "Are You Listening?" featuring women who work as domestic employees and maids. Issues of respect, education, and benefits are discussed from the point of view of the household technician.
  - Art of Seeing (Reel AV 1898)
    Short film presented by the American Federation of Arts about the perception of light, color, shape, and other physical concepts we see. Demonstration of seeing aspects of natural, scientific, and artistic elements. An ACI Release.
  - At the Time of Whaling (Reel AV 1908)
    Film produced by and about the small Eskimo village of Gambell, on St. Lawrence Island in Alaska. Includes footage of whale hunting, a village-wide activity, as well as singing and dancing, cooking, family relations, and other Eskimo traditions in their general village life. Copyright 1975, the Village of Gambell and Leonard Kemerling.
  - The Arab World's Past and Future, 1958 (Reel AV 1905)
    One of 15 lectures in a series entitled "A Changing World in the Light of History". Given by Arnold J. Toynebee at Washington & Lee University, Lexington VA, 1958. Produced by James Sage for Encyclopedia Brittanica. Copyright 1958.
  - The Arab World's Past and Future (Part Two), 1958 (Reel AV 1416)
  - Award-Winning Innovations in State and Local Government, 1988 (Reel AV 1432)
    Presentation of social welfare programs in Kentucky, San Diego, and other cities around the U.S. Funded by the Ford Foundation and other organizations, these initiatives provide housing, food, education, and healthcare for a range of displaced people in need.
  - Battling Brook, 1968 September 3-7; Silent, Black and white, 1 minute. (Reel AV 2010)
    Unedited footage of people waling in and out of Battling Brook Primary School.
  - Battling Brook, 1968 September 3-7 (Reel AV 2009, Reel AV 2012)
    Shot during 1968 September 3-7, this film explores the first four days after summer vacation of children ages 8-11 years old learning in a nontraditional schooling environment in Leicestershire, England. Produced in cooperation with the Public Education program of the Ford Foundation. Copyright 1969, Henry Felt.
    Existence and Location of Copies
    2 copies on 16mm.
  - Balanced and Unbalanced Forces, 1957 (Reel AV 1504)
    An educational short film produced by Encyclopedia Brittanica as part of their course in physics, filmed in Pittsburgh public schools. With Processor Harvey E. White, University of California. Copyright Encyclopedia Brittanica Films Inc.
  - Behavior of Gases, 1959 (Reel AV 1421)
    An educational short film produced by Educational Resources Inc as part of their course in physics for secondary school systems. With Dr. Albert V. Baez.
  - Benjamin E. Mays: A Great Georgian, 1974 (Reel AV 1976)
    Documentary film based on the autobiography "Born to Rebel" of Morehouse College president Benjamin E. Mays. Film includes interviews with Dr Martin Luther King Sr., Jimmy Carter, Coretta Scott King, Samuel DuBois Cook, Edward B. Williams and John Danforth. Produced with a grant from the Ford Foundation. Grant # 75-31. Copyright University of Georgia, 1974.
  - Benin Kingship Ritual (Reel AV 1920)
    Demonstrations of political and religious rites of the Oba, or King of the Benin region of West Africa. Footage of the Igua Blessing, Odudna Masquerare, and the Ugie-Erha-Oba Festival, with explanatory narrative. Produced for the Benin Historical Research Scheme by F.E. Speed and R.E. Bradbury.
  - Blackman's Burden (Reel AV 1889)
    Short film examining post-colonial issues in under-developed nations, as seen by third world residents and their wealthy neighbor nations. Discusses issues of education and access, agriculture and industry, international economics, and the basic struggles of people in need. Written and directed by Richard Broad. Thames Colour Production.
  - Brothers and Sisters in Concert, 1974 (Reel AV 2013A, Reel AV 2013B, Reel AV 2013C, Reel AV 2013D, Reel AV 2013E, Reel AV 2013F)
    A concert film shot in Chicago during a five day business and arts exposition sponsored by Operation PUSH (People United to Save Humanity) with performances by Marvin Gaye, The Staple Singers, The Temptations, The Chi-Lites, The Main Ingredient, The O’Jays, Isaac Hayes, Zulema, The Cannonball Adderly Quintet, The Push Mass Choir, Albertina Walker, Loretta Oliver, Rev. James Cleveland, Bill Withers, Curtis Mayfield, Sammy Davis, Jr., Roberta Flack, Quincy Jones, Gladys Knight and the Pips, Jerry Butler, Brenda Lee Eager, The Ramsey Lewis Trio, Nancy Wilson and the Jackson 5. Copyright 1974, PUSH Foundation.
  - California Vs. Green (Reel AV 1890)
    Reenactment of a court case to illustrate methods of communication and interrogation in a court room. Produced by Charles Lesson and Eric Saltzman, with support from the National Endowment for the Humanities.
  - Canadian Conference on Education (Reel AV 1907)
    Demonstration of the Tan-Gau method of secondary language instruction, as presented to a a group of Canadian 5th grade students. A teacher from Toronto, Raymond Duplantie, uses the Tan-Gau method to introduce basic vocabulary. Lessons 1 and 2 are shown, based on the work on Dr. Tan-Gwan Leong and Dr. Robert Gauthier. Produced for the Canadian Conference on Education and the Ford Foundation, with the Metropolitan Educational Televisions Association. A CFTO Production.
  - Career Education (Reel AV 2007)
    A documentary film about career education to equip young people with ideas about entering the industrial or commercial occupational fields. With an introduction from S.P. Maryland, Jr. Assistant Secretary for Education, Department of Health, Education and Welfare.
  - Carnot Cycle and Kelvin Cycle, 1951 (Reel AV 1881)
    Film from the "Basic Physics Series" about light and heat reactions, to be used in the classroom. Produced by McGraw-Hill Text Films, in collaboration with the Visual Aids Committee of the American Association of Physics Teachers. Copyright 1951, McGraw-Hill Book Company.
  - Citizens Conference (Reel AV 1811)
    Documentary about issues in the education system, as demonstrated by schools in Montgomery County, Maryland. Poor communication between staff and students, unequal rights, overly strict polices, etc. are discussed in interviews and montages. "The questions we have tried to raise, and the points of view expressed, mainly reflect the interests of the only group involved in this problem, whose voices won?t be heard, that of the students".
  - Citizens Conference, Sound, Black and white, 28 minutes. AV 2244A is magnetic tape. AV 2244B is a workprint. (Reel AV 2244A, Reel AV 2244B)
    Documentary about issues in the education system, as demonstrated by schools in Montgomery County, Maryland. Poor communication between staff and students, unequal rights, overly strict polices, etc. are discussed in interviews and montages. "The questions we have tried to raise, and the points of view expressed, mainly reflect the interests of the only group involved in this problem, whose voices won't be heard, that of the students".
  - Challenge in Africa, 1978 (Reel AV 1839)
    Film about the work of the International Committee of the Red Cross in Africa; efforts to provide food, housing, and healthcare for Africans throughout the continent affected by war, civil unrest, and lack of infrastructure. Footage of battlegrounds in Chad, medical camps in Botswana, Rhodesian refugees, interviews with doctors and nurses working in rural clinics, etc. Some graphic footage.
  - Changing Work, 1975 (Reel AV 1797)
    Documentary about six American auto workers who spend time in a Saab factory in Sweden to learn about different trends of workplace design and organization. Their program was organized by Cornell University, Industrial and Labor Relations, under a grant from the Ford Foundation. Directed and edited by Peter Goldmann. Produced by Bjorn Ericstam, Sandell. Film, with Executive Producer David Hancock. Copyright maintained by the Ford Foundation.
  - Collision of Hard Spheres, 1960 (Reel AV 1424)
    An educational short film featuring Dr. James S. Strickland, produced by Educational Resources Inc. as part of their course in physics. Funded by the Alfred P. Sloan Foundation, the National Science Foundation, and the Ford Foundation.
  - Color (Reel AV 1873)
    Brief science film explaining the physics of color, presented by the American Federation of Arts. Produced by ACI, with funding from the Ford Foundation.
  - Command Post, 1955 February 27 (Reel AV 1808)
    Introduction to the US Air Force's plans during the Cold War. The Continental Air Defense Command is introduced during a visit to an underground military base on Long Island, codenamed "COBRA". Anti-Soviet defenses, aviation technology, and national emergency preparedness are discussed. Version is incomplete, film ends suddenly.
  - The Common Good: New York State Legislature in Action (Reel AV 2018)
    A documentary about he inner workings of New York State's Legislature filmed in Albany, New York at the State Capitol based on an idea by Albert J. Abrams, secretary of the Senate. Narrated by Dave Garroway. Written and Directed by David Epstein.
  - The Common Good: Social Welfare and the American Future, 1990 (Reel AV 2019)
    This film is based on the report and reccommendations of the Ford Foundation project on socil welfare and the American Future. The documentary offeres new ways to think about child care, welfare, the working poor, displaced workers, healthcare, the ederly, addiction issues and homelessness. It was produced for the Ford Foundation by Dick Young Productions, Ltd. New York City. Copyright 1990, Dick Young.
  - Communication and the Judge (Reel AV 1882)
    Dramatized examples of courtroom behavior and communication, targeted at students of the California College of Trial Judges. Produced at UCLA for Los Angeles County, by the California College of Trial Judges.
  - Community Leadership Institute, 1953 July (Reel AV 1806)
    Film report by the Fund for Adult Education, of the Ford Foundation, about an experiment in designing and supporting community leaders. 275 local leaders from all over the United States were invited for a two-week retreat of workshops and discussions on resolving community issues, communication tools, local resources, and other topics. Narrated by John Vacca, the delegate from Odessa, Texas. Filmed at Bigwin Inn in Ontario, Canada.
  - Continental Classroom: Nuclear Rhythms (Reel AV 1846)
    An introduction to the Continental Classroom film series and its early research in educational TV programming and satellite education. An initial summary of pilot programs precedes Episode 147 of the series,"Nuclear Rhythms", with Dr. Felix Bloch (director of the Manhattan Project). The series was funded by the Ford Foundation, Standard Oil Company of California, the Fund for the Advancement of Education, and many others. Produced by NBC and the American Association of Colleges for Teacher Education.
  - Cotton (Reel AV 1975)
    Footage of Paul Miller and the Board of Central Rose Memorial Hospital accepting a grant from the Ford Foundation for a hospital expansion program. The film also includes footage of hospital rooms, nurses and patients, hospital exterior, and architectural drawing of "addition" to the Central Rose Memorial Hospital.
  - Coulomb Force Constant (Reel AV 1989)
    An educational film about the Coulomb Force Constant funded by the National Science Foundation, Alfred P. Sloan Foundation and Ford Foundation as part of its course in physics for secondary schools.
  - Counting Electrical Charges in Motion, 1960 (Reel AV 1852)
    An educational short film featuring Dr. James S. Strickland. Funded by the Alfred P. Sloan Foundation, the National Science Foundation, and the Ford Foundation. Produced by Educational Resources for the Physical Science Study Committee, as part of their course in physics.
  - Definite and Multiple Proportions, 1960 (Reel AV 1791)
    An educational short film featuring Professor Robert C.C. St. George, Cambridge School of Weston, and Professor Jerrold R. Zacharias, MIT. Funded by the Alfred P. Sloan Foundation, the National Science Foundation, and the Ford Foundation. Produced by Educational Resources Inc. for the Physical Science Study Committee as part of their course in physics.
  - Deflecting Forces, 1958 (Reel AV 1991)
    An educational film about deflecting forces funded by the Natioanl Science Foundation, Alfred P. Sloan Foundation and Ford Foundation as part of its course in physics for secondary schools with experimental demonstrations by Nathaniel H. Frank, Chairman of Department of Physics, MIT. Copyright 1958, Educational Services Inc.
  - Dr. Vrick (New York University), c. 1958 (Reel AV 1793)
    An education professor from Texas speaks about current issues in US schools, comparing with systems in Russia and evaluating data from the past 15 years.
  - Education in Eskimo (Reel AV 1792)
    A documentary about bi-lingual education in Eskimo communities in Alaska. The title in Eskimo is Elitnaureyaraq Yupigtun. Produced by the US Department of the Interior, Juneau Area Office.
  - Elastic Collisions and Stored Energy, 1961 (Reel AV 1807)
    An educational short film featuring Dr. James S. Strickland of the Physical Science Study Committee. Funded by the Alfred P. Sloan Foundation, the National Science Foundation, and the Ford Foundation; produced by Educational Resources Inc. as part of their course in physics.
  - Electronic Residence: TAGER 1968 (Reel AV 1953)
    Demonstration of the TAGER system, a closed-circuit educational television program designed to share resources and professors at the university level. Designed by a consortium of Texas universities, including Austin College, Texas Christian University, University of Dallas, and others, the TAGER system formed to unify research and education resources for advanced study, at the graduate level and beyond.
  - Der Heimliche Schrittmacher (Reel AV 1969)
    A short film from the German series "Alternativen", about the Ford Foundation work in impoverished urban areas. Homeless shelters and programs to help addicts are shown, as well as administrative planning and the new Ford Foundation headquarters in Manhattan. Brief graphic footage of monkeys being inoculated.
  - Elementary Charges and Transfers of Kinetic Energy, 1960 (Reel AV 1959)
    An educational film presented by the Physical Science Study Committee as part of its course in physics, with Dr. Francis L. Friedman of MIT. Funded by the National Science Foundation, Alfred P. Sloan Foundation, and the Ford Foundation. Copyright 1960, Educational Services Inc.
  - Elliptic Orbits, 1959 (Reel AV 1425)
    An educational short film produced by Educational Resources Inc. as part of their course in physics for secondary school systems. With Dr. Albert V. Baez.
  - The Empirical Formula of a Compound, 1958 (Reel AV 1786)
    Episode #14 from an educational series "Chemistry: An Introductory Course", taught by Dr. John F. Baxler from the University of Florida. Produced by Encyclopedia Britannica.
  - Energy and Work, 1959 (Reel AV 1801)
    An educational short film produced by Educational Resources Inc. as part of their course in physics for secondary school systems. With Professor Dorothy Montgomery, chairman of the Department of Physics, Hollins College.
  - Erie Environment, 1976 (Reel AV 2185, Reel AV 1840)
    Short film about environmental management in Erie County, NY. Local officers and citizens worked with the State Department of Environmental Resources, the Department of Sanitation, and the Department of Health to improve water quality and environmental management. Local, ground-level efforts are shown to be more effective than centralized government programs. Produced by John Karol and Apertura, in cooperation with the Erie County Department of Health. Copyright 1976, the Ford Foundation.
  - Erie Environment, 1976; Silent, Color, 19 minutes, A Roll. (Reel AV 2219A)
    FORD FOUNDATION FILM ABOUT ENVIRONMENTAL MANAGEMENT IN ERIE COUNTY, NY: LOCAL OFFICES AND CITIZENS WORKED WITH THE STATE DEPT OF ENVIRONMENTAL RESOURCES, DEPT OF SANITATION, AND DEPT OF HEALTH TO IMPROVE WATER QUALITY AND ENVIRONMENTAL MANAGEMENT. LOCAL, GROUND-LEVEL EFFORTS ARE SHOWN TO BE MORE EFFECTIVE THAN CENTRALIZED GOVERNMENT PROGRAMS. PRODUCED BY JOHN KAROL, PRESENTED IN COOPERATION WITH THE ERIE COUNTY DEPARTMENT OF HEALTH (COPYRIGHT FORD FOUNDATION, 1976)
  - Erie Environment, 1976; Silent, Color, 19 minutes. (Reel AV 2219B)
    FORD FOUNDATION FILM ABOUT ENVIRONMENTAL MANAGEMENT IN ERIE COUNTY, NY: LOCAL OFFICES AND CITIZENS WORKED WITH THE STATE DEPT OF ENVIRONMENTAL RESOURCES, DEPT OF SANITATION, AND DEPT OF HEALTH TO IMPROVE WATER QUALITY AND ENVIRONMENTAL MANAGEMENT. LOCAL, GROUND-LEVEL EFFORTS ARE SHOWN TO BE MORE EFFECTIVE THAN CENTRALIZED GOVERNMENT PROGRAMS. PRODUCED BY JOHN KAROL, PRESENTED IN COOPERATION WITH THE ERIE COUNTY DEPARTMENT OF HEALTH (COPYRIGHT FORD FOUNDATION, 1976). Includes the animated titles featured in release print.
  - Erie Environment, 1976; Soundtrack, 19 minutes. (Reel AV 2219C)
  - Experiment on Elasticity, air date: 1958 November 11 (Reel AV 1854)
    Soundtrack to Continental Classrooms, show #45.
  - Experiment on Elasticity, air date: 1958 November 11 (Reel AV 1426)
  - Experiment on Elasticity, air date: 1958 November 11 (Reel AV 1850)
  - Exploratorium, 1975 (Reel AV 1855)
    Film about the Exploratorium Science Museum in San Francisco, CA. Interactive exhibits about light, sound, energy, and other natural phenomena are shown, using optical illusions, kinetic artworks, displays of frequency and pitch, and other methods. The end of the film shows the museum founder, Dr. Frank Oppenheimer, discussing the impact of the exhibits with the staff. This film was shot by Jon Boorstin and funded by the National Education Association and the National Science Foundation. Copyright 1975, Jon Boorstin and the Exploratorium.
  - For Fair Play (Reel AV 2195)
    Presented by the Pennsylvania State Commission on Industrial this film is a dramatization of desegregation in Bellefonte, Pennsylvania. It is from a white male prepective and he tries to imagine how hard it would be to get a job based on skin color.
  - Ford Foundation Talk (Reel AV 2192, Reel AV 2236, Reel AV 2237)
    Negative print of a man being interviewed. Possible H. Rowan Gaither interview.
  - The Fragile Mountain, 1982; Part 1 (AV 1812 and AV 1804) and Part 2 (AV 2212). (Reel AV 1812, Reel AV 1804, Reel AV 2212)
    A 2-part documentary about climate change in the Himalayas, and the effects of environmental shifts on populations and governments. Focuses on Nepal, India, and surrounding nations, showing discussions with villagers, eco-friendly farming technologies, new fuel sources, etc. Produced by Sarah Nichols Productions, with funding from the Ford Foundation. Copyright Sandra Nichols Productions, 1982.
    Renewable energy sources -- Developing countries; Renewable natural resources
  - Franklin Thomas: Guild Hall lecture (Reel AV 1979)
    Franklin Thomas giving a lecture at Guild Hall.
  - Gaither and the Ford Foundation Interview
    Interview of H. Rowan Gaither regarding the current state of education in America in the 1950s. Gather discusses his views on education and the role that private citizens and corporations should play in education.
    - Ford Foundation Talk, Silent, black and white negative, 10 minutes. (Reel AV 2192)
    - Ford Foundation Talk, Soundtrack, 10 minutes. (Reel AV 2262)
    - Ford Foundation Talk, Silent, black and white negative, 10 minutes. (Reel AV 2236)
    - Ford Foundation Talk, Sound, 10 minutes. (Reel AV 2262)
    - Gaither Interview, Sound, black and white, 30 minutes. (Reel AV 1885)